Bruce Jackson and Diane Christian collection
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
- Series 2: Sound Recordings
  - Subseries 7: Politics and news
    - 688 / News, 1970-1972, 1974, AFC 2011/009: SR0551; 1 sound tape reel: analog, 3 3/4 ips; 7 in.
      - Side 1
      - 1. George McGovern, Hubert Humphrey - Meet the Press, May 28, 1972
      - 2. Nixon press conference on Laos, March 3, 1971
      - Side 2
      - 1. Nixon on Nixon: Nixon's seventh crisis - CBS special (lots of quick cuts and juxtapositions by them), January 9, 1974
      - 2. Lowell We[?] - ABC [TV] Issues and Answers, January 13, 1974
      - 3. M[?], January 15, 1974
      - 4. B[?] of Ron H[?] on Nixon tape erasure, January 15, 1974
    - 689 / McGovern and Humphrey 1972 / Jerry Rubin 1970, 1970, 1972, AFC 2011/009: SR0552; 1 sound tape reel: analog, 3 3/4 ips; 7 in.
      - Side 1
      - George McGovern on Dick Cavett, December 12, 1972
      - Today Show: Nixon on end of the Viet Nam war, s[?] Mansfield, Scott, etc. Vets in Walter Reed [hospital] / Kissinger Congress that [?], June 23, 1973
      - Side 2
      - Hubert Humphrey at Macedonian Baptist Church ([?]), May 23, 1972
      - Jerry Rubin at UB [SUNY-Buffalo] 1970 (?) recorded off the air WSFO [radio], 1970
    - 529 / Nixon Resignation 1, August 8, 1974, AFC 2011/009: SR0483; 1 sound tape reel: analog; 5 in.
      - Nixon Nix
      - Side #1 6:00-9:00 P.M.
      - News special - John Chancellor
    - 530 / Nixon Resignation 2, August 8-9, 1974, AFC 2011/009: SR0484; 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in.
      - Side 1, August 8, 1974
      - 1. Nixon quits
      - 2. Post Morums [?]
      - Side 2, August 9, 1974
      - 1. Nixon departs
      - 2. News flashes
      - 3. Ford sworn in and speech
    - 531 / Nixon / August 13, 1974 [?], August 13-14, 1974, AFC 2011/009: SR0485; 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in.
      - Side #1, August 9, 1974
      - News 6:00-7:30
      - Special on Channel 2 (10 P.M.)
      - News 11:00-11:30
      - CBS - Special - Channel 4 - 11:30
      - 2 Presidents: Transition in White House
      - News local #2 National 2 CBS, August 12, 1974
      - Side 2
      - National
      - Ford Speech August 13
      - August 13, Local #2 NBC and CBS News (6:00-7:30)
      - August 14, 1974
    - 840 / Ford State of Union, January 12, 1977, AFC 2011/009: SR0668; 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in.
    - 732 / William Shockley and Roy Innes (CORE) debating Tomorrow Show, December 12, 1973, AFC 2011/009: SR0634; 1 sound tape reel: analog; 5 in.
      The forum was The Tomorrow Show, with host Tom Snyder. William Shockley (Nobel prize-winning physicist) and Roy Innis (National Director of CORE [the Congress of Racial Equality] debated Shockley's low Black IQ notion ["Are Blacks Genetically Inferior to Whites in Intelligence?"].
    - 838 / Malcolm X, March 17, 1964, AFC 2011/009: SR0666; 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in.
      Malcolm X speaking at Harvard University, with James Q. Wilson and Martin Kilson. The recording was made with a mic at a speaker, so there is significant noise. This dub copy is "filtered" (according to the tape box back). The date is give on the tape box spine as March 17, but sources online indicate March 18.
    - 839 / Dick Gregory, February 25, 1964, AFC 2011/009: SR0667; 1 sound tape reel: analog, quarter track, mono; 7 in.
      Boston civil rights rally, with Theo Bikel, Jim Bede[?]. The original was recorded as 7 1/2 ips, half track mono. The actual boycott (the second "Stay Out for Freedom") took place on February 26. It is unclear if the recording was made the day before the boycott,or is a recording of part of the boycott. This dub of Bruce Jackson's tape was made as a quarter track mono. It was recorded off the air, from a WGBH (Boston) broadcast.
  - Subseries 8: Dubbed recordings
    Dubs of commercial recordings and from tapes at other repositories.
    - Cheap Thrills - Big Brother and the Holding Company/ New York Tendaberry - Laura Nyro, 1968-1969, AFC 2011/009: SR0904; 1 sound tape reel: analog; 5 in.
    - David's Album - Joan Baez / VSD 79308, 1969, AFC 2011/009: SR0944; 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in.
      Dubs of commercial recordings.
    - AAFS LP Master / Wahsons [?], undated, AFC 2011/009: SR0949; 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in.
      May include part of Afro-American Spirituals, Work Songs, and Ballads (AFS 13).
    - DF-214 / Prison Worksongs from Library of Congress / AAFS-LOC LWO-4471, undated, AFC 2011/009: SR0578; 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in.
      Prison Worksong Master, side 1. A label on the tape box partially obscures information about the tape contents.
    - Live Dead - Grateful Dead, 1969, AFC 2011/009: SR0928; 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in.
      This may be a dub recording of a commercial release by the Grateful Dead or, based on various notes on the tape box back, may be non-commercial recordings.
    - Guthrie / Stones / Fahey / Beatles / S. Smith, undated, AFC 2011/009: SR0953; 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in.
    - 740 / "Roll on John", 1946, AFC 2011/009: SR0625; 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in.
      "Roll On, John," sung by Palmer Crisp, Allen, Kentucky 1946, and recorded by Margot Mayo and Stu Jamieson [Robert Stuart Jamieson]. This is probably AFS 08503, in the collections at the American Folklife Center. If so, further details are available regarding this recording.
    - John Mayall, undated, AFC 2011/009: SR0687; 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in.
      Dubbed recordings from commercial releases: The Blues Alone (London PS 534), A Hard Road (London PS 502), USA Union (Polydor 24-4022)
    - Ben Botkin / 8-19-63, August 19, 1963, AFC 2011/009: SR0830; 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in.
      Dubbed from 78 rpm discs owned by Ben Botkin. A list appear on the tape box back.
    - 761 / Buddy Moss / Too tight Henry Diamond Joes, undated, AFC 2011/009: SR0841; 1 sound tape reel: analog, 7 1/2 ips, mono; 7 in.
      This tape seems to be a compilation of songs from commercial recordings.
    - Cowboy and Sailor, undated, AFC 2011/009: SR0905; 1 sound tape reel: analog; 5 in.
      A compilation of dubbed recordings from various non-commercial sources.
    - Dock Boggs / Bessie Jones / Sacred Harp / Fisk Jubilee 1913, undated, AFC 2011/009: SR0906; 1 sound tape reel: analog; 5 in.
      Probably a compilation of recordings, both commercial and non-commercial.
      - Oh Death - Dock Boggs
      - Oh Death - Bessie Jones
      - Sacred Harp
      - Glory Glory Hallelujah
      - Roll Jordan Roll - Fisk Jubilee (1913)
    - Them / Otis Redding / Fugs, undated, AFC 2011/009: SR0907; 1 sound tape reel: analog; 5 in.
      Dub of commercial recordings.
    - The Origin of the Blues / Blues and Entertainment / The Thirties Urban and Rural Blues / WWII and After, undated, AFC 2011/009: SR0935; 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in.
      Dub copy of a commercially-released compilation of recordings: The Story of the Blues (Columbia G 30008).
    - 698 / Fairuz at the International / Oriental Bouquet / Abdallah, undated, AFC 2011/009: SR0936; 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in.
      Dub copy of commercial recordings by Fairuz and by Abdallah Chahine.
    - 732 / I. Instrumental Music of the S Appalachians / II. New Orleans Jazz, undated, AFC 2011/009: SR0937; 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in.
      Dub copy of commercial recordings. Labels on the box have the name of the Archives of Folk and Primitive Music, Indiana University.
    - 868 or 898 / Brand / Kingston Trio / Burl Ives, undated, AFC 2011/009: SR0938; 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in.
      Dub copy of commercial recordings.
    - 183 / Bill Broonzy, undated, AFC 2011/009: SR0939; 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in.
    - Folklore Class Tape #2 / Prof. Jackson Dept. English, undated, AFC 2011/009: SR0945; 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in.
      Compilation of archival and commercial recordings.
    - Gabor Szabo / Charles Lloyd / H. Silver, undated, AFC 2011/009: SR0946; 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in.
      Compilation of commercial recordings.
    - Blues Sampler, undated, AFC 2011/009: SR0947; 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in.
      A compilation of commercial recordings.
    - Blues Sampler, undated, AFC 2011/009: SR0954; 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in.
      A compilation of recordings by Robert Pete Williams, John Lee Hooker, Mississippi John Hurt, Bessie Smith, Memphis Slim, and others. These recordings may have been dubbed from commercial releases.
    - Cowboy, undated, AFC 2011/009: SR0948; 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in.
    - Anglo American Folksong Style, undated, AFC 2011/009: SR0950; 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in.
      Possibly a dub of one of the AFS commercial releases.
    - 699 / Yugoslavian Narrative with guslar accompaniment I, undated, AFC 2011/009: SR0838; 1 sound tape reel: analog, 7 1/2 ips, two track, mono; 7 in.
      Tape copy of commercial discs in the collection of Zora Dvernja. Tape 1 has 7-inch discs, 33 rpm).
    - 700 / Yugoslavian Narrative with guslar accompaniment II, undated, AFC 2011/009: SR0839; 1 sound tape reel: analog, 7 1/2 ips, two track, mono; 7 in.
      Tape copy of commercial discs in the collection of Zora Dvernja. Tape 2 has 7-inch discs, 45 rpm).
  - Subseries 9: Various sound recordings
    - Dubbed with my cassette # 25 / Side 2, August 25, 1970, AFC 2011/009: SR0678; 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in.
      Jackson recorded interviews with Black migrant workers in Barker, New York. The manuscript log is in his handwriting.
    - 605 / "Painted Post Country", May 6, 1969, AFC 2011/009: SR0547; 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in.
      Painted Post is a village in New York State. Ken Thomas may have been a student of Jackson.
    - 606 / "Painted Post Country"/ Ken Thomas, May 6, 1969, AFC 2011/009: SR0548; 1 sound tape reel: analog; 5 in.
      See notes for SR0547.
    - 607 / Lebanese songs, AFC 2011/009: SR0549; 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in.
    - 748 / dub for Bruce Jackson, November 4, 1960, AFC 2011/009: SR0561; 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in.
    - 895 / Arthur Boose: WOB spiel / Von Schmidt: Garfield, AFC 2011/009: SR0571; 1 sound tape reel: analog; 5 in.
      "WOB" may refer to the Wobblies.
      - 1. Arthur Boose, Portland, Oregon; recorded by B.A. Botkin and Stewart Holbrook, August 31, 1950
      - 2. Eric von Schmidt: James A. Garfield
    - LF3 [?], AFC 2011/009: SR0576; 1 sound tape reel: analog; 5 in.
      The writing on the tape box is indistinct.
    - 735 / Amarillo Holiness Church, July 1967, AFC 2011/009: SR0577; 1 sound tape reel: analog, 1 7/8, quarter track, mono; 5 in.
      J.B. Smith sent this tape to Jackson. According to Jackson's note on the tape box: "part is service, with some good singing, part prayer meeting."
    - Utah Sings! / "The Working Class Hero" / Part 1, possibly 1977, AFC 2011/009: SR0615; 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in.
      This may be Utah Phillips.
    - 736 / Calypsos, 1968, AFC 2011/009: SR0627; 1 sound tape reel: analog; 5 in.
      Side 1 recorded in San Juan by Bill Sylvester; first [?]; boys from St. Thomas singing. Further details on the tape box.
    - 816 / "ASS" LP master tape / AA. Jackson, undated, AFC 2011/009: SR0636; 1 sound tape reel: analog; 5 in.
      Bruce Jackson Toast LP, Side A. The title for this LP in the LC catalog is "Get your ass in the water and swim like me!": narrative poetry from the Black oral tradition (edited by Bruce Jackson; produced in conjunction with the Center for Studies in American Culture, SUNY Buffalo and the Society for Traditional Music). Originally released 1998.
    - 817 / "ASS" LP master tape / AA. Jackson, undated, AFC 2011/009: SR0637; 1 sound tape reel: analog; 5 in.
      Bruce Jackson Toast LP, Side B. See notes for SR0636.
    - A5 or 45, undated, AFC 2011/009: SR1148; 1 sound cassette (90 min.): analog
    - Vincent Gange / 1970 / English 383, 1970, AFC 2011/009: SR0840; 1 sound tape reel: analog, 3 3/4 ips; 7 in.
      According to the tape box back: "This tape was prepared by Vincent Gange in the Fall of 1970 for English 383 [class]. It accompanies other, written materials on the Seneca Indians on the Cattaraugus Indian Reservation, near Gowanda, N.Y. It includes a recording of 'The Feather Dance,' performed at Seneca ceremonies."
    - Use [the only word on the back of the tape box not crossed out], undated, AFC 2011/009: SR0902; 1 sound tape reel: analog
    - Black Narr [narrative?], undated, AFC 2011/009: SR0908; 1 sound tape reel: analog; 5 in.
    - [No information on the tape box], undated, AFC 2011/009: SR0927; 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in.
    - 10/20/1976, October 20, 1976, AFC 2011/009: SR0940; 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in.
      Handwriting on the tape box is too faded to read. The recording is assumed to be related to SR0941.
    - Doc Gary Galetta / Mark Donahue / Steve Hassett, undated, AFC 2011/009: SR0942; 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in.
    - Gary Galetta / Interview with Jo Watson / Robert Weiss, undated, AFC 2011/009: SR0943; 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in.
    - I Spanish G[?], undated, AFC 2011/009: SR0955; 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in.
      Modest amount of information on the tape box has faded.
    - HHH, undated, AFC 2011/009: SR0956; 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in.
      No other information on the tape box.
    - 386-389 / Oversize - in case 3, undated, AFC 2011/009: SR0957; 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in.
    - Judy / Samples / For the Jacksons [DF-207], circa 1970s, AFC 2011/009: SR0958; 1 sound tape reel: analog, 3 3/4 ips, two track; 7 in.
      A sampler of folk music recorded in Illinois, Indiana, and Arkansas, by Judy McCulloh.
    - Tom Pickard Soundtrack, undated, AFC 2011/009: SR1220; 1 sound cassette (60 min.): analog
    - 7 / Jim - interview, undated, AFC 2011/009: SR1234; 1 sound cassette (90 min.): analog
    - 8, undated, AFC 2011/009: SR1235; 1 sound cassette (90 min.): analog
    - 9, undated, AFC 2011/009: SR1236; 1 sound cassette (90 min.): analog
    - 10, undated, AFC 2011/009: SR1237; 1 sound cassette (90 min.): analog
    - 11, undated, AFC 2011/009: SR1238; 1 sound cassette (90 min.): analog
    - #90 / Thursday 11-12, undated, AFC 2011/009: SR1258; 1 sound cassette: analog
    - #92 / Thursday 1-2 / 222 Scully, undated, AFC 2011/009: SR1259; 1 sound tape reel: analog, 10 in.
    - #93 / Thursday 12-1 / 224 Scully, undated, AFC 2011/009: SR1260; 1 sound tape reel: analog, 10 in.
    - #94 / Thursday 10-11, undated, AFC 2011/009: SR1261; 1 sound tape reel: analog, 10 in.
- Series 3: Graphic Materials
  - Photos, undated, 3 black-and-white photos: 5 x 6 in. and smaller (Box-folder 4/10)
  - "Painted Post Country," undated, 10 color slides: 35 mm (Box-folder 4/11)
- Series 4: Moving Images
  Processing work in progress. The list of projects minimally processed so far reflects only the contents of this collection, and is not exhaustive. Bruce Jackson and Diane Christian have collaborated on the following films: Death Row, Robert Creeley: Willy's Reading, William August May, Out of Order, Creeley, and Robert Creeley: The Persistence of Verse (a conversation between Robert Creeley and Bruce Jackson, 2001). Both directed, edited, and produced these films. Jackson did the cinematography and Christian recorded the sound. Running times for all films are approximate. Descriptions of these films, and other film highlights from the collection, appear below.
  - "Hard Language," 1974
    Jackson and Christian organized this symposium at SUNY-Buffalo (now University at Buffalo). Participants included: Leslie Fiedler (American critic), Angus Fletcher (literary scholar), Frederick Jameson (critic), René Girard (literary theorist), Neville Dyson-Hudson (anthropologist), William Bossert (mathematical biologist), Roger Abrahams (folklorist), Richard Macksey (literary scholar), Nathan Lyons (photographer and photo historian), Jackson, and Christian.
  - Death Row, 1979
    Jackson conducted extensive interviews with inmates on death row at Ellis Unit, in Texas. The film documents the daily lives of the inmates, from work to recreation, from mealtimes to their personal thoughts about their lives and imminent fate. Some employees of the prison are also interviewed. 60 min.
  - Services Rendered, 1979
    Jackson produced, did sound, and some camera for this film, which was directed by Andy Ferullo. Approximately 15 vignettes of working people in Buffalo, at work and talking about their work. 60 min.
  - I Found a Feather, 1980
    A short fiction film Jackson did not finish. He shot the footage near Buffalo, in the Alabama Swamp Complex, part of the Iroquois National Wildlife Refuge (with its headquarters located in Alabama, New York).
  - Robert Creeley: Willy's Reading, 1982
    In this film Creeley reads drafts of a poem he wrote to honor the birth of Willy, his son. 16 min.
  - William August May, 1982
    A documentary about William August May, a lifelong deep water fisherman, and the changes to the California environment he has observed. 18 min.
  - Michael McClure, 1982
    An unfinished documentary on the life of poet Michael McClure.
  - Out of Order, 1983
    Interviews with six former nuns, as they talk about their lives as nuns and after leaving holy orders: what made them decide to join and later why they left, as well as their experiences readjusting to the secular world. Diane Christian, a former nun, is one of the interviewees. 89 min.
  - Creeley, 1988
    A film about Creeley's background and development as a poet, including interviews with him and others, plus conversations with him. 59 min.
  - William Kunstler, 1988
    An unfinished documentary on the life of civil rights leader and formidable lawyer William Kunstler. 18 min.
  - Robert Creeley: the Persistence of Verse, 2001
    A conversation between Creeley and Bruce Jackson. 17 min.
  - Cummins Wide: Photographs from the Arkansas Prison, 2008
    Footage taken at Cummins Unit, a prison in Lincoln County, Arkansas. Jackson had considered making a film during the time he was making the photographs that would be in Killing Time, Inside the Wire, Cummins Wide, and other books and exhibits. With that future project in mind, he shot this footage, using a Sony Portapak. According to Jackson, he used an edited version of this footage to get a grant to help fund the making of Death Row.